Finding Aid for the James J. Lang Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
James J. Lang Papers
1981-1998
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0249
1.26 linear feet
Biography/History
James J. Lang received his B.A. degree from Canisius College in 1966. His doctoral work in sociology and demography was completed at the University of Michigan. He served as a Vista Volunteer at Southside Settlement House in Columbus, Ohio and worked as a Project Director for Crossroads Africa in Gambia, West Africa.
Professor Lang held a position in Sociology and Latin American Studies at Vanderbilt University from 1974 to 2008. His research and field work has been supported by the American Council of Learned Societies, the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, the Kellogg Foundation, the Rockefeller Foundation, the International Potato Center, and Vanderbilt’s Faculty Research Council.
Between 1988 and 1998, he visited nine countries for his book Notes of a Potato Watcher, College Station: Texas A & M University Press, 2001. The field notes are from the following countries: Peru, Bolivia, Ecuador, Tunisia, Egypt, Kenya and Uganda, India, and Indonesia.
Between 1981 and 1984, he visited thirty-four development projects in six countries: Costa Rica, Brazil, The Dominican Republic, Colombia, Paraguay, and Argentina. The field notes from the Dominican Republic, Brazil, and Colombia provided the raw materials for Inside Development in Latin America, Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1988. These materials were received in Special Collections in 2002.
In 1989 Professor Lang took a trip to Brazil, and in 1990 to Asia to meet with people from the IRRI (International Rice Research Institute). Topics discussed include research testing of rice, salt and iron tolerance in rice, weed control, and production. His field notes are contained in two bound volumes titled, Feeding a Hungry Planet.
Professor Lang provided a biographical sketch and a bibliography, which is included with the finding aid.
Scope and Contents
This collection, measuring .66 linear feet, contains three series of field notes:
Series I, housed in 12 acid-free file folders, relates to Notes of a Potato Watcher, covers potato crops, viruses that effect the potato, research into ways to prevent the viruses, genetic engineering of the potato, production, pests, and breeders. File folders follow the format from the table of contents. Note: An abstract written by Professor Lang is included with the finding aid.
Series II, housed in six acid-free file folders, relates to Inside Development in Latin America, covers the principle problems in each country, outlining some programs that may improve conditions in education, health care, and agriculture. File folders are in alphabetical order. The following field notes are included in the collection:
Series III contains two bound volumes of field notes Chapter One: Asia- Feeding a Hungry Planet, and Chapter Two: Brazil-Feeding a Hungry Planet.
- SERIES I NOTES OF A POTATO WATCHER
  Overview and Table of Contents
- Peru
  - July 12, 1988 to July 25, 1988 (Box 1)
  - March 11, 1996 to March 12, 1996 (Box 1)
  - May 12, 1997 to May 15, 1997 (Box 1)
- Bolivia
  - April 3, 1990 to April 12, 1990 (Box 1)
  - February 28, 1996 to March 6, 1996 (Box 1)
- Ecuador
  - April 28, 1997 to May 9, 1997 (Box 1)
- Tunisia
  - June 28, 1996 to July 5, 1996 (Box 1)
- Egypt
  - July 9, 1996 to July 11, 1996 (Box 1)
- Kenya & Uganda
  - December 9, 1997 to January 6, 1998 (Box 1)
- India
  - December 16, 1996 to January 3, 1997 (Box 1)
- Indonesia
  - October 19, 1995 to November 17, 1995 (Box 1)
- SERIES II INSIDE DEVELOPMENT IN LATIN AMERICA, Overview
- Brazil
  - March 2, 1982 to July 2, 1982 (Box 2)
  - July 11, 1983 to July 22, 1983 (Box 2)
- Colombia
  - May 7, 1983 to June 17, 1983 (Box 2)
- Costa Rica
  - November 17, 1981 to December 10, 1981 (Box 2)
- Dominican Republic
  - January 3, 1983 to January 12, 1983 (Box 2)
- Series III FEEDING A HUNGRY PLANET
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH: JAMES J. LANG
Dr. James Lang grew up in Buffalo, New York, where he received his B.A. degree from Canisius College in 1966. As a college student, he spent his summers as a steel worker at the Bethlehem rolling mill in Lackawanna, New York. He did his doctoral work in sociology and demography at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. At Michigan, Dr. Lang was a founding member of the first Residential College. Before completing his graduate studies, he served as a Vista Volunteer at Southside Settlement House in Columbus, Ohio. He also spent a summer as a Project Director for Crossroads Africa in the Gambia, West Africa. As an advanced degree candidate, Lang held a Danforth-Kent Doctoral Fellowship.
From 1974 to 2008, Dr. Lang held a position in Sociology and Latin American Studies. His research and field work has been supported by the American Council of Learned Societies, the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, the Kellogg Foundation, the Rockefeller Foundation, the International Potato Center, and Vanderbilt’s Faculty Research Council.
Dr. Land participated in Vanderbilt’s Faculty-in-Residence Program and is a recipient of the Chancellor’s Cup for service to Vanderbilt students. He is fluent in both Portuguese and Spanish and is a past Director of Vanderbilt’s residential language program at Vanderbilt’s McTyeire International House.
Dr. Lang’s published work has focused on comparative history and development. Conquest and Commerce: Spain and England in the Americas (New York: Academic Press, 1975) compares the colonial regimes that Spain and England established in the New World. Portuguese Brazil: The King’s Plantation (New York: Academic Press, 1979) examines how the formation of an export-dominated economy shaped Brazil’s development. Inside Development in Latin America (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1988) looks at how community-focused, self-help projects are organized; examples come from the Dominican Republic, Columbia, and Brazil. Feeding a Hungry Planet (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1996) is about how grassroots technology transformed rice production in Asia and Latin America. Notes of a Potato Watcher (College Station: Texas A & M University Press, 2001) describes Andean agriculture, explains how potatoes became a staple crop throughout the world, and analyzes potato production projects in Asia, Latin America, and Africa.